[Music]
hello and welcome to a brand new episode
of smart money on today's episode we do
a deep dive on how you can select the
right health insurance plan what are the
things you need to evaluate before
picking your health insurance and we'll
also help you with an age-wise breakdown
on how much Insurance you need at what
age what are the premiums you need to
pay for it as well joining us in the
show is Girish naak he's the chief
technology health and officer at ICI
Lombard Gish thanks a lot for joining us
on CNBC TV8 uh well you know I want to
first start with what the importance of
health insurance is in today's economy
because a lot of young people a lot of
people reach out to me saying we just
don't know how to start our insurance
Journey so what is your advice to them
thank you Sonia for having me on the
show and uh like you said it's a very
important uh topic because uh not many
people are really aware of health
insurance uh and it's a very important
aspect of financial planning U health
insurance costs uh the healthcare costs
are rising and the medical costs are
really rising and uh almost every year
we have 63 million Indians who actually
fall below poverty line uh because of
healthcare uh costs and that's a huge
number so uh planning for a financial
emergency is extremely important and
health insurance helps you to do that
now there are many kind of health
insurance two main kinds are basically
uh the group insurance and the
individual insurance most of us are
familiar with the group insurance
policies which uh you have with your
employer the employer will have a group
insurance policy and uh all the
employees are typically covered by it
there's also the individual insurance
policies where you can take it as a
individual and there are many kinds of
uh individual insurance policies that
you have but I think what is more
important that every individual should
have some sort of health insurance
policy to protect against unforeseen
medical uh emergencies that's very
important I want to talk a little bit
about that right because all of us
employees have a corporate policy uh but
you spoke about the different types of
health insurance there's group health
insurance there is individual health
insurance so for someone who already has
corporate Insurance do you need to take
a top up do you also need an individual
health insurance can you just explain a
little more sure see Group insurance
policies typically will all employees in
a group and uh the cover is generally
around four to 5 lakhs uh per individual
some employees also offer uh coverage to
maybe spouse spouse children if the
employees are very generous spouse
children parents so there are different
kinds of cover that uh employers provide
but most of these covers are typically
around four to 5 lakhs and that really
doesn't suffice for a family uh health
insurance uh cover so it is always
advisable to to have an individual
insurance cover as well now normally uh
also what happens is when you are in
employment you typically don't worry
about this thing saying that your kind
of employee is going to cover you and
you'll be on until retirement but when
you retire say at the age of 60 and
suddenly you realize you are without a
cover at that point in time going and
getting cover will be very expensive
unless you had a cover from a
significantly earlier age so that's one
reason why you should get a health
insurance cover even though you have a
group Insurance Group cover that is
covering you the other U other thing is
that uh the uh coverage of the group
insurance policy is typically limited to
what the employer kind of uh decides for
you here you as individual you can kind
of uh have a lot more add-ons that you
want which are more suited to your
requirements and hence uh having an
individual insurance policy is always
better than just having only the group
insurance cover that you normally go
with okay so we are talking about the
advantages of of personal uh retail
insurance right so individual insurance
basically uh you spoke about how you get
to decide what the cover can be as
opposed to your you know employer
deciding and the other thing is when you
retire you will not just be left without
an insurance so always better to have an
individual not only when retire say for
example you quit your job quit your job
and want to become an entrepreneur yes
at that point in time again you you
might be wanting to set out on the
exciting Journey but it's better if you
have a individual cover at that point in
time okay so you at least the any
Healthcare emergency is covered so when
you're seeing a corporate insurance you
have that you do a top up or you take a
separate individual insurance policy
again there there are multiple options
that you you can take uh a separate
individual insurance policy is always
best because it covers you right from
the base so tomorrow like for example I
said if you go out of the corporate job
and you want to start off on your own
you have a cover right from base but yes
some people from point of view of their
budget would want to take a topup uh
policy so so top-ups are much cheaper
than the uh taking a full cover so if
you want to take uh a cover for say 15
lakhs and your uh employer is giving you
uh 3 lakh cover you say take a topup
which will cover you from 3 lakhs to 15
lakhs so that will be cheaper than
taking a full 15 lakh cover but at the
same time you should realize that when
your Group Insurance stops the first
three lakhs will still be need to be
covered by you so you need that base
cover at some point in time so again
it's advisable to take a individual uh
complete insurance policy and just a
topup uh if you can afford it okay I
want to talk about starting insurance at
a younger age right what are the
benefits of buying health insurance at a
younger age and what age is the right
age to
start good question I mean uh it's
always good to start early uh again from
a health insurance point of view uh the
healthier the life the lower the
insurance younger uh customers always
have a lower Insurance uh premium and
given our lifestyles today and the kind
of uh stress that is there uh invariably
you see people over 40 45 ending up
having some kind of a lifestyle uh
whether it's hypertension blood the
diabetes India is the diabetes capital
of the world so once you have any of
these when you get into a insurance
policy at that point in time these get
marked off as pre-existing diseases and
your cover the premium is always higher
but if you're already on a policy and
you contract that's there your premium
should would not change because there
you didn't have those uh conditions when
you contracted the policy so it's always
better to get in at early age um when
you start your career start off with
insurance policy okay I want to
understand is health insurance a tax
saving tool or should you look at it
separately well there there is advantage
of tax saving as well because uh uh uh
you have up to age of 60 years you can
uh cover yourself and your family and
under Section 80d you get a cover of up
to 25,000 of a premium you can uh set
off uh if you're covering a parents uh
who are above 60 then you get additional
50,000 uh set off under the U section 8D
so there okay but you shouldn't look at
it as a tax saving tool right that's a
added benefit it's an added benefit it's
added benefit so you when you want to do
your financial calculations it does help
saying that okay this much is coming
back to me as a tax saving but I would
look at it purely as a protection which
you need because one is making
Investments to grow your Capital but
this kind of protection for your capital
in case there is any emergency you don't
draw from your Capital to pay for it so
you have something which takes care of
that uh absolutely absolutely so I do
want to know how much health insurance
do I need age- wise right but what I'm
going to do is I'm going to take a short
commercial break don't go anywhere when
we come back we'll tell you how to plan
your health insurance to secure your
future and just a
bit well on this week's episode of smart
money we talk about how you can pick the
right health insurance and what are the
things that you need to do before you
select your insurance plan uh Girish n n
is with us Gish what are the you know
how is the procedure right how do you
select the right health insurance plan
yeah good question um there are
different kinds of individual uh
insurance plans that are available so
the first basic one which you understand
is the indemnity plan which typically
covers you when uh you hospitalized so
your expenses during hospitalization are
covered by uh the plan there are also
what we call the benefit plans so uh
this kind of gives you a fixed payout uh
if you contract a certain illness like
for example a cancer benefit if you
contract cancer it'll pay out a lumps
some amount which you take the insurance
for without going into whether you take
the treatment or not that's not uh issue
but in in the previous case in Indemnity
uh you have to actually get hospitalized
and take the treatment it is reimbursing
your actual costs there's also personal
accident policies which cover uh uh you
against accidents and all so that's uh
the different kinds of health plans you
there the other uh aspect is a good one
for typically need a Indemnity plan
definitely okay definitely need a COR
plans are mostly Indemnity plans
corporate plans are mostly Indemnity
plans uh which cover you for
hospitalization now Indemnity plans also
come with multiple you uh as a family uh
you can also purchase a what is called a
floater because uh when you take an
individual plan uh say you take a 10
lakh plan for an individual then it
covers you for a 10 lakhs but if you are
a family of for two adults two children
you can cover the entire family on a
floater for 10 lakhs then any one of
them incurring expenses of up to 10 lakh
is covered the total uh family incurring
expens of up to 10 lakh is covered so it
need not be any one of them can incur
the expense it's covered so one year
someone can uh incur the expense other
year other one can multiple people can
incur the expense within the plan as
long as total is about 10 lakhs okay I
have a question here you earlier said
that a corporate plan u a lot of
generous corporates sort of include your
parents also in the plan right but what
happens when if and when you leave the
job
uh to your parents I mean you can take a
separate plan but largely these
individual plans don't include parents
who are above the age of 60 so what
happens then how do you uh safeguard
that so you have senior citizens plans
also okay so a lot of uh insurers have
uh plans for which cover senior citizens
of course the premium is a bit higher
out there uh naturally but uh that's
something that is available okay so uh
you can use a senior citizen plan to
cover uh parents again and like I said
there's also a tax angle to it because
you cover your parents and uh up to
50,000 of Premium you can set off in
your taxes in your taxes okay and how do
I settle my insurance claims that is you
know because there's cash list there is
reimbursement uh a lot of corporates
have cashless uh Insurance processes as
well uh but what is the process like so
typically uh the cashless process works
for both corporate as well as individual
uh insurance claims so if the typically
if the hospital is within the insurers
Network then you can go to the hospital
and uh there'll be a TPA desk out there
where you give your papers and the uh
cashless approval is given by the
insurer and based on that the hospital
treats you without you having to pay out
any uh some some from your pocket but if
that is not available you can also go
into reimbursement which is basically
you make the payment and then give the
bills to your insurer to reimburse you
for the cost of incard uh cash always
better because you don't have to sell
out anything from your pocket and this
and uh some ins I we we are definitely
offering a anywhere cashless facility
which is basically even if the hospital
is not within our Network so our network
is about 7,500 hospitals but uh even if
the hospital is not within our network
if you intimate us 48 hours prior to
your hospitalization then we can arrange
a cash Less in that hospital as well
okay so that's a that's a great benefit
to uh to be associated with a bigger
brand like ICS LOM got it at industry
level now we are having this initiative
where everyone is trying to move to a
cash lless anywhere that should be out
soon but we we already had have had it
for uh almost a year now so you don't
have that stress of you know oh there's
only a certain amount of hospitals in
your list where you have to sort of you
know go and get your treatment or else
you won't get cash so all that is going
to be uh sorted out yeah once we have
this uh cashless anywhere cashless
anywhere okay I want to understand
different scenarios right just real life
examples if I'm a 25y old if I'm a 33
year old I'm a 40y old what is the kind
of insurance that I need so let's start
with the age of 25 in that age group uh
how much Insurance do I need how much
cover do I need yeah we have a yeah
typically uh uh 25 year old I'm assuming
single uh just started off on the job uh
would 7 and a half lakh uh insurance
would be good enough of course there are
tax benefits which and that's 10,000
would be the approximate premium
including taxes uh which one would have
to pay P so uh this 7 and2 lakhs you're
saying is uh largely corporate insurance
has about 5 lakhs so you're saying if
someone is 25 and has a 5 lakh corporate
insurance you have to take an additional
insurance or some short of better take
insurance from uh the beginning and what
happens if you don't claim the insurance
then uh you get a bonus which is called
additional sum insured which gets added
to the uh cover some covered every year
and depending on the insurer this could
go up to uh 50 or 100% of the sum
insurance so if you're getting covered
by coroporate insurance and you're not
claiming on this uh Insurance soon this
will with the additional summon insur
this could go up to 15 lakhs on its own
okay because of the additional sum
insured okay now let's move on to
someone who's say 33 years old has maybe
just got married or is planning to have
a child right what is the kind and is a
corporate employee what is the kind of
insurance that they need yeah say that
they would need to up their cover a bit
uh make it about uh 10 lakhs and uh
would have a floater policy covering
both self and spouse so that would be U
better and of course you would have
add-ons because your requirements would
have increased you would have a
maternity benefit which would be uh
important again uh newborn baby cover
OPD some PL offer OPD not all insures
offer OPD because most of the individual
insurance is uh in patient treatment
that is you need to get hospitalized but
there are plans and like we do have
plans which offer uh out patient
treatment which is basically your
consultation your Diagnostics your
Pharmacy charges so uh you can buy OPD
add-on which covers all these uh
benefits so that is something that uh
they could cover on this okay let's move
on to the age group of say 45 to 60
right uh what is the kind of insurance
that they need and since that's an age
which is a tricky slightly tricky one uh
okay we have your 45-year-old
businesswoman who's married um that's a
tricky one because that's really the age
when you start developing some health
issues as well so how do you plan it so
like I said plan from before but at this
point in time you typically uh say have
uh couple of kids so two adults two kids
uh 25 lakh policy uh again uh is 25 laks
enough these
days I'm just giving you a base you can
always there are policies which now
offer 50 one CR yeah we have now
launched a unlimited coverage so oh
really I didn't know that that okay we
just launched it okay what does that
include it it's all your everything but
without a limit for coverage okay so and
so there's the extra premium for that
perhaps the premium is uh higher
obviously but uh for again for those who
can afford they can buy that coverage
and it covers you worldwide as well okay
so any cost incurred when you travel
anywhere again like I said for this uh
profile You' also need uh annual Health
checkups so if your plan offers you
anual Health checkups that should get
covered because at the age of 45 you
start doing your health doing your
health checkups more regularly than when
you are 25 right I know I know I
understand uh so what about retirement
right there are some people who have hit
the age of 60 suddenly developing a lot
of health issues but have no insurance
so what do they do we have here a
59-year-old pensioner has pre-existing
medical conditions perhaps diabetes some
even have critical Ines like cancer Etc
so what do they do if they don't have
insurance yeah so so typically it's very
difficult if you have developed a
critical inness like cancer to get a
policy okay um because that is uh what
you call a non- insurable risk uh as but
if you have diabetes if you have
hypertension there are policies that you
can get the premium will be higher and
again as a good practice again it's
always better to declare your
pre-existing illness to the insurer
before taking the policy okay that's a i
a lot of people uh undergo stress at
time of claims because they have not
declared or have forgotten to mention
any pre-existing illness and diabetes
and hypertension are the most common
ones that fall into this category
someone doesn't mention that uh he or
she has had diabetes when uh getting or
has hypertension and getting the policy
when it gets found out during a claim
the claim gets rejected and you have
these other issues that turn up so it's
always better to declare upfront uh
because there'll be some loading on the
premium but you'll get the policy so for
uh uh person who's retired without a
policy you would require a cover which
typically again has annual checkups you
would add the Outpatient Treatment OPD
because there would be a lot of um at
that age you would necessarily need to
see the doctor much more often than you
see at a younger age so that's a kind of
policy you would take with about 15 lakh
cover at least and a floater again for
self and spouse and that would be in the
range of about say 50,000 okay okay one
final question then um a lot of people
get sold ulips right so I mean I know
it's a very tricky topic but just
demystify it for us should people go for
your lips or not see I I am strictly
against it because I believe that your
investment should be absolutely separate
from your insurance perfect that's the
right way to look at it and that's a
life insurance uh link policy of course
of health is health is separate health
is sold without a yeah without an
investment angle to it without it's
protection for your investment I mean
that's how you look at it but for life
insurance for term insurance say for
example you think it needs to be a
separate policy all together term is I
mean you should take a Term Policy as
well because that is important but take
a Term Policy it's simple Insurance
that's uh that's that's so no to you
lips again investment and protection
should be separate okay that's what you
believe that's again uh to make it more
simple that that would be a but Health
we don't have that uh it's it's purely
protection uh look at it as protection
for your Investments and for your health
yeah okay all right gir thanks a lot for
joining in appreciate you taking the
time out and speaking to CNBC TV8 with
that it's a wrap on Smart money thanks a
lot for
watching